Guide to the Branko Grujic Papers ALBA.127
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Branko Grujic Papers
1937-1956
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Grujic, Branko, 1904-1956
ALBA.127
1.5 Linear Feet in 1 manuscript box and 1 oversize flat box
Branko Grujic was a Romanian-born Canadian who fought in the Dimitrov Battalion of the 15th Intenational Brigade during the Spanish Civil War. This collection consists of correspondence, notebooks, memorabilia, and documents issued to him during this time, as well as during the Second World War.
Provenance
The Branko Grujic Papers were donated to the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives by Margaret Fishman, in 1997. This collection came to New York University in January 2001 as part of the original acquisition of ALBA collections, formerly housed at Brandeis University.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Historical/Biographical Note
Branko Grujic was born in Sfântu Gheorghe (St. George), Romania on August 15, 1904. In 1937, he joined the Dimitrov Battalion of the 15th International Brigade, a battalion whose members consisted primarily of Balkan and Eastern European volunteers. The Dimitrov Battalion was later incorporated into the 129th International Brigade. Grujic fought in an anti-tank outfit.
After the Spanish Civil War, Grujic was naturalized as a British citizen and, in 1945, as a Canadian by Imperial certificate. He served with the Canadian military during World War II as an explosives specialist. He died in Canada in 1956.
Scope and Content Note
This small collection consists of two series. Series I: Spanish Civil War Files, 1937-1939, includes official documents (identification cards, medical records/receipts, etc.), notebooks, and memorabilia that Grujic acquired during his time in Spain.
Series II: General Files, 1940-1956, consists of notebooks, correspondence, and memorabilia, dating primarily from the period of World War II. It also includes correspondence in Serbian, presumably with family members.
Grujic's surname appears in many permutations throughout the collection, and this finding-aid uses the spelling that appears most consistently, and that conforms to Serbian usage. His given name also occurs in a variety of forms, including "Stanko," "Brance," and "Stanley."
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically.
The files are organized into two series:
Missing Title
I, Spanish Civil War Files, 1937-1939.
II, General Files, 1940-1956.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Branko Grujic Photographs. (ALBA Photo #127)
ALBA collections at the Tamiment Library.
Memorabilia.; Correspondence.; Money.; Barcelona (Spain); Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |x Participation, Romanian.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Personal papers.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |x Participation, Yugoslavian.; Jarama River Valley (Spain); Madrid (Spain); Biography files.; Official documents.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Songs and music.; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Brigada Internacional, XV -- biography.; Grujic, Branko, 1904-1956; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Abraham Lincoln Battalion
- Series I: Spanish Civil War Files. 1937-1939.
  - Carnet Militar, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Certificate of Retirement from the International Brigades, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Clippings: Pictures and Captions on Dimitrov Battalion and Individual Balkan Volunteers, from Nuestro Espana, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Currency: Spanish Republican ("Vales"), 1937-1939 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Ejercito de Levante: Homage to the International Fighters `, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Identification Questionnaire ("Filacion"), 1938 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Leaflet: Invitacion Personal al Homenaje, Dedicado a los Voluntarios Internacionales, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Leaflet for Spanish Movie, "Diego Corrientes", undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Leaflet Dropped by Loyalist Air Force for International Brigade Soldiers, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - League of Nations: Certificate of Retirement from the International Brigades, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Map of Aragon, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Medical Records, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Notebook: Diary/Spanish Vocabulary, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Notebook: Spanish-Serbian Vocabulary, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Notebook: Travel Log and Notes on Front Activities, 1927-1938 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Note (in Serbian), undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Pamphlet: La Declaracion de Principiod del Gobierno de Union Nacional (Comisariado de la 129 Brigada Internacional), with Names Written on Back, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Safe Conduct Pass, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Socorro Rojo: Membership Card, Stamps, Contribution Receipt, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Stamps and Bus Tickets, 1937-1939 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Text of War Songs (Serbian), undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Series II: General Files, 1940-1956.
  - Arm Patch Issued by Canadian Army, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Clipping: Gas Attack Chart (British ARP), 1941, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Clippings: Yugoslavian Soldiers, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence (Serbian), undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence: Gruici, Budinca, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence: Truiuk, Ilya, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Currency: International, 1940-1944 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Home Guard: What the H.G. Needs to Know about Explosives, by Chas C. Knight, 1940-1949 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Identification Cards, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Interment Card, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Notebook: Address/Notes on Explosives, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Notebook: English-Serbian Vocabulary, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Obituary (Serbian), 1956 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Passport (Canadian), 1945 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Painting (named spelled "Stanko Gruich"), 1937 (Box 2)